Humanistic Studies, Institute for; Records ua444
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Institute For Humanistic Studies Records
1977-1980
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
ua444
3.33 cubic ft.
Faced with major cutbacks in support for the Humanities in the mid-1970s, the Institute for Humanistic Studies was created to stimulate research and critical thinking in the Humanities on the State University of New York at Albany campus.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Acquisition Information
These records were donated to the M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives, University Libraries by M.E. Grenander, Director of the Institute for Humanistic Studies.
Biographical History
The Institute for Humanistic Studies was founded in 1977 by Professors M.E. Grenander (Director, 1977-80), and Hugh Maclean (Deputy Director, 1977-?), "to serve as an organizational umbrella under which both mature and promising scholar-teachers can conduct humanistic research and scholarship at relatively advanced levels...." and also "to provide leadership for humanistic disciplines, and to serve as a platform for cooperation with other departments and schools at SUNYA that may an interface with the humanities."[1] The Institute consisted of a group of thirty State University at Albany faculty Fellows, experienced research scholars who achieved eminence in such fields as literature, philosophy, history, sociology, political science, economics, urban affairs, criminal justice, and anthropology. They were selected each year by a nation-wide Distinguished Advisory Council of ten members, who collaborated with Grenander and Maclean, "in developing plans for establishing the Institute at SUNYA"[2].
In the adverse fiscal climate of the middle and late 1970's, the Institute was created to encourage mutually supportive humanistic research and to make it available in many forms to a broad audience. This concept was facilitated by the Institute through sponsorship of events, such as, monthly luncheons at which faculty fellows presented papers and discussed their research interests, and conferences (local and international) on such topics as the humanities and solar energy, the humanities and computers, libertarian humanism and the philosophical idea of "representation". The Institute also participated in a college lecture series, "The Idea of a University--Revisited", fall 1977, and in the planning of a lecture series of 14 dates titled, "Thantos: Perspectives on Dying", to be held at the Empire State Plaza in the fall of 1979 and the winter of 1980. The lecture series was cancelled due to administrative difficulties, and it is unclear whether the series was ever presented. The Institute also published a newsletter, The Conjugator, three times annually from 1978-1980, and proceeding of the three conferences it sponsored.
The centerpiece of Institute activities was its sponsorship of a series of conferences in the late 1970's. The Institute's first conference "HELIOS: From Myth to Solar Energy" was held March 16-18, 1978, investigated "man's age long interest in and dependence on the sun, examined from a humanistic perspective and culminating today in his adaptation of solar energy."[3] The second conference, "APOLLO AGONISTES: The Humanities in a Computerized World," held April 19-21, 1979, attempted to demonstrate "that the computer can not only help the humanist to solve those of his problems which depend on vast, accurate memory and extraordinarily rapid calculations, it also demonstrates that whatever answers it gives the humanist, they are never final."[4] The third conference, "ASCLEPIUS AT SYRACUSE; Thomas Szasz, Libertarian Humanist," held April 17-19, 1980, brought together speakers from United States, Canada, and England to analyze Szasz's writings. The speakers used history and literature to "examine his perspective on culturally determined institutions for oppression," giving particular emphasis to Szasz's "role in the development of changing attitudes toward social and legal controls vs. civil rights.[5]
After the resignation of M.E. Granander in 1980 the Institute appeared to play a less active role, but continued to be listed in the University phone directory as a unit of College of Humanities and Fine Arts until the fall of 1985. Members of the Institute were consulted in the development of the Doctor of Arts in Humanities Program in 1982.[6] Martin Kane was listed as Director of the Institute from 1980-82. Berel Lang, the head of the Doctor of Arts Program in the Humanities was listed as the prospective leader of the institute in 1983.[7]
[1] Accent on Research, October, 1977, pg. 2-3.[2] Accent on Research, October 1977, pg. 2-3.[3] Proposal letter from M.E. Grenander, October 5, 1977.[4] Proceedings - APOLLO AGONISTES: The Humanities in a Computerized World, 1979, p. xx.[5] Proceedings - ASCLEPIUS AT SYRACUSE: Thomas Szasz, Libertarian Humanist, 1980, p xvi[6] College of Humanities and Fine Arts, Five Year Plan, January 1982, p. 21. Office of President Records, Box 80.[7] College of Humanities and Fine Arts Five Year Update, June 1983, p. 5. Office of President Records, Box 80.
Scope and Contents
The records of the Institute were kept by Dr. M.E. Grenander, first director of the Institute for Humanistic Studies from its founding in 1977 until her resignation in 1980. They document the conferences and meetings held by the Institute. Specifically, these files contain administrative records related to the creation, funding, and programs of the Institute; M.E. Grenander's correspondence with conference participants regarding proposal for presentations; draft program proposals and accepted papers for each conferences; published conference verbatim conference proceedings including: HELIOS: From Myth to Solar Energy, 1978; APOLLO AGONISTES: The Humanities in a Computerized World, 1979; and AESCLEPIUS AT SYRACUSE: Thomas Szasz, Libertarian Humanist, 1980; and The Conjugator, 1978-80, a periodic newsletter of the Institute. Also included in the files are copies of newspaper articles about the conferences, photographs taken at each conference, and scrapbooks of the three conferences as kept by M.E. Grenander.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection has four series, arranged alphabetically.
UAlbany Centers & Institutes; State University of New York at Albany. Institute For Humanistic Studies
- Director's Administrative Correspondence, 1975-1981; 1; 0.5 cubic ft.
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically.
  Scope and Contents
  Contains correspondence, publicity, grant requests relating to the founding, financing, and running of the Institute, and each individual conference organized by the Institute. Includes correspondence with the national Board of Overseers, and lists of Institute faculty fellows.
  - Director's Administrative Correspondence, Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Additional Funding Sources, 1975-1978 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Apollo Agonistes: Rockefeller Foundation --A/L 320-903-A, 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Annual Report, 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Annual Report, 1978-1979 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - CEAA Subvention-- National Endowment/Humanities, 1974-1976 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Commission on the Humanities, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Department Chairmen, 1976-1978 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Four Interdisciplinary Books-- National Endowment For the Humanities, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Grant Requests: Psychiatry Szasz, 1975-1977 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Humanities Commission Review, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - "The Idea of a University- Revisited"- Flyers, 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Info. For Brochure Charge, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - National Endowment for the Humanities, 1976 March-1979 August (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - New York Council for the Humanities, 1975-1981 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - President's Office, 1975-1977 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - President Vincent O'Leary, 1978-1980 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Programs/Other Conferences, 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Publicity, 1978 May 10 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Requests for Information about HIS, 1978-1985 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Rockefeller Foundation, 1976-1977 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Spencer Foundation, 1975-1977 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - SUNY Central, 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - SUNYA Administration, 1975-1978 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - SUNYA Bibliography, 1975 November 25 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Theoretical Studies, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Director's Conference Correspondence, 1977-1980; 2; 1.5 cubic ft.
  Arranged chronologically by conference date and alphabetically thereunder.
  Contains correspondence with potential speakers, funding and annual financial reports, brochures, newspaper and journal clippings relating to three international conferences: "Helios: From Myth to Solar Energy," 16-18 March, 1978; "Apollo Agonistes: The Humanities in a Computerized World," 19-21 April, 1979; "Asclepius at Syracuse: Thomas Szasz, Libertarian Humanist," 17-19 April, 1980. Also includes correspondence and program related material for a planned local lecture series of 14 dates titled, "Thanatos: Perspectives on Death," which was to be held from the fall of 1979 through the winter of 1980. The Conference was never held.
  - Council, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Andrews, John Frank, 1976-1979 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Arnstein, Walter, 1976-1978 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Boyd, William, 1976-1980 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Goffman, Erring, 1976-1982 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Hague, John A., 1976-1980 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Harris, Neil, 1976-1979 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Holman, C. Hugh, 1976-1980 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Lewalski, Barbara K., 1976-1980 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Rosenblum, Victor, 1976-1978 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Taylor, Joshua C., 1976-1981 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Denmark, 1977-1979 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - France, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Germany, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Sweden, Lund University, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Sweden, Uppsala, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - U.S.S.R., Moscow, 1978-1980 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - USSR; Tbilisi in Georgia Kakabaze Art Museum, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Atmospheric Sciences Research Center, 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Grant Requests and Reports New York Council for the Humanities, 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Helios Proceedings--Volume One Publication Unbound, 1978 March 16-1978 March 18 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Helios Proceedings--Volume Two Publication Unbound, 1978 March 16-1978 March 18 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Info. For Fellows & Contributors, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Program, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Public Relations/Press, 1978-1980 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Publications/Abstracts, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Solar Energy Project: Energy, Society, and the Sun, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Solar Energy Project: Sunschooling, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Solar Energy Project: Sunstory, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Solar Energy Project:Sunworks, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Correspondence A-B, 1977-1980 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Correspondence C-E, 1977-1980 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Correspondence F-G, 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Correspondence H-K, 1977-1979 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Correspondence L-M, 1977-1981 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence N-Q, 1977-1979 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence R, 1977-1979 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence S, 1977-1980 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence T, 1977-1978 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence U-Z, 1977-1979 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Misc. Correspondence N-Z, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Clippings I, 1978-1982 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Clippings II (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Foreign Speakers (Non-participants), 1978 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Grant/Funding Correspondence & Information, 1977-1979 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Humanities Studies-Institute, 1977-1982 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Interest Letters, 1978-1979 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - National Endowment for the Humanities--Apollo Agonistes Grant Proposal, 1978-1979 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Proceedings Apollo Agonistes: The Humanities in a Computerized World Vol.2, 1979 April 19-1979 April 21 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Proceedings Requests, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Program and Conference Info., 1979 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Public Relations, 1978-1980 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Speakers,--yes Kiasashuili, Nico, 1978-1986 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Speakers,--yes Utas, Bo, 1978-1980 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Apollo Agonistes Correspondence, Undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence A-B, 1978-1980 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence C-E, 1978-1979 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Correspondence F-G, 1978-1984 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Correspondence H-K, 1978-1980 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Correspondence L-M, 1978-1982 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Correspondence N-Q, 1978-1981 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Correspondence R, 1978-1981 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Correspondence S, 1978-1980 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Correspondence T, 1978-1979 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Correspondence U-Z, 1978-1980 (Box 2, Folder 31)
- Institute Publications, 1977-1980; 3; 0.5 cubic ft.
  Arranged by series publication.
  Includes The Conjugator: Vol. I, No. 1-3, 1977-78; Vol. II, No .1-3, 1978-79; Vol. III, No. 1-3, 1979-80, the Institute newsletter, and published conference proceedings: Helios: From Myth to Solar Energy, Vol. I & II, 16-18 March, 1978; Apollo Agonistes: The Humanities in a Computerized World, Vol. I & II, 19-21 April, 1979; Asclepius at Syracuse: Thomas Szasz, Libertarian Humanist, Vol. I & II, 17-19 April, 1980.
  - Conversations in the Discipline, 1979-1980 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Koch Foundation, 1979-1981 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Liberty Fund/Indianapolis, 1979-1981 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - National Endowment for the Humanities, 1971-1980 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - The New York Council for the Humanities, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - The New York State of Mental Health, 1979-1981 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Public Relations, 1979-1981 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Program, 1979-1980 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - SUNY Alliance, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Symposium Banquet, 1980 May 9 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence A-G, 1979-1980 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence H-O, 1979-1980 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence P-R, 1980-1981 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence S-Z, 1979-1986 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, 1978-1980 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - The Conjugator Vols. 1-3, 1977-1978; 1979-1980 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Proceedings Helios: From Myth to Solar Energy Vol. 1, 1978 March 16-1978 March 18 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Proceedings Helios: From Myth to Solar Energy Vol. 2, 1978 March 16-1978 March 18 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Proceedings Helios: From Myth to Solar Energy Vol. 2, 1978 March 16-1978 March 18 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Proceedings Apollo Agonistes: The Humanities in a Computerized World Vol.1, 1979 April 19-1979 April 21 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Proceedings Asclepius at Syracuse: Thomas Szasz, Libertarian Humanist Vol.1, 1980 April 17-1980 April 19 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Proceedings Asclepius at Syracuse: Thomas Szasz, Libertarian Humanist Vol.1, 1980 April 17-1980 April 19 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Proceedings Asclepius at Syracuse: Thomas Szasz, Libertarian Humanist Vol.2, 1980 April 17-1980 April 19 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Proceedings Asclepius at Syracuse: Thomas Szasz, Libertarian Humanist Vol.2, 1980 April 17-1980 April 19 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Apollo Proceedings--Volume Two Publication Unbound, 1979 April 19-1979 April 21 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Proceedings Apollo Agonistes: The Humanities in a Computerized World Vol.2, 1979 April 19-1979 April 21 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Institute Scrapbook, 1977-1978 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Institute Scrapbook, 1978-1979 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Institute Scrapbook, 1979-1980 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Asclepius at Syracuse: Thomas Szasz, Libertarian Humanist, 1990 April 17-1990 April 19 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Apollo Agonistes Conference, 1979 April 19-1979 April 21 (Box 3, Folder 31)
- Scrapbooks, 1978-1980; 4; 0.5 cubic ft.
  Arranged by conference.
  Contains brochures, The Conjugator, flyers, photographs, and articles relating to the institute's three conferences: "Helios: From Myth to Solar Energy", 16-18 March, 1978; "Apollo Agonistes: The Humanities in a Computerized World", 19-21 April, 1979; "Asclepius at Syracuse: Thomas Szasz, Libertarian Humanist", 17-19 April, 1980. There are four scrapbooks in all, one for each individual conference, and the last one contains material on all three conferences.
  - Flyers, 1978-1980 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - "Helios: From Myth to Solar Energy" Vol.1 Proceedings 16-18 March 1978, 1978 April 16-1978 April 18 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - "Helios: From Myth to Solar Energy" Vol.2 Proceedings 16-18 March 1978, 1978 April 16-1978 April 18 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - "Apollo Agonistea: The Humanities Vol.2 in a Computerized World", 1979 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - "Asclepius at Syracuse: Vol.1 Thomas Szasz, Libertarian Humanist" Proceedings 17-19 April 1980 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - "Asclepius at Syracuse: Vol.2 Thomas Szasz, Libertarian Humanist" Proceedings 17-19 April 1980 (Box 4, Folder 6)